<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Elephant Man and Other Reminiscences</title>
                <author sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/265340794">Frederick Treves</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <persName>AP, VD</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Electronic Edition</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>0.28 MB</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Project Gutenberg</publisher>
                <date>2019/07/06</date>
                <idno type="Gutenberg">59865</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>This eBook is for the use of anyone anywhere in the United States and most other parts of the world at no cost and with almost no restrictions whatsoever.  You may copy it, give it away or re-use it under the terms of the Project Gutenberg License included with this eBook or online at www.gutenberg.org.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct xml:lang="en">
                    <monogr>
                        <title>The Elephant Man and Other Reminiscences</title>
                        <author>Frederick Treves</author>
                        <imprint>
                            <date>1923</date>
                            <pubPlace sameAs="https://www.geonames.org/2643743/london.html">London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher sameAs="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q5049289">Cassel and Co LTD</publisher>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>The purpose of the TEI encoding of some paragraphs of the book "The elephant man and other reminiscences" is to develop a LOD progect about Joseph Merrick for the "Information Science and Cultural Heritage" course </p>     
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>The original text has been transcribed faithfully without additions or modifications, except for the indication of omitted paragraphs. No content editing or typographical corrections have been made.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The provided text is not complete and contains only the paragraphs 1, 4 and 56 with omission indicated by "[...]". There is no italicized text.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc>
                <channel mode="w">print</channel>
                <constitution  type =" single "/>
                <derivation  type =" original "/> 
                <domain  type =" education "/> 
                <factuality type="fact"/> 
                <interaction type="none"/>
                <preparedness type="revised"/>
                <purpose type="inform"/> 
            </textDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <name>London, Great Britain</name>
                    <time>Late 19th century</time>
                </setting>              
            </settingDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person xml:id="Treves" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/265340794">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Frederick</forename>
                            <surname>Treves</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <occupation>Doctor</occupation>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Merrick" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/62352264">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>John</forename>
                            <surname>Merrick</surname>
                            <addName type="nickname">The elephant man</addName>
                        </persName>
                        <residence notAfter="1890" sameAs="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q7374421">London Hospital</residence>
                        <residence notBefore="1886">
                            <placeName>
                                <settlement sameAs="https://www.geonames.org/2643743/london.html">London</settlement>
                                <region>Great Britain</region>
                            </placeName>
                        </residence>
                    </person>
                    <person xml:id="Showman" sameAs="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q7817056">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Unknown</forename>
                            <addName type="nickname">Showman</addName>
                        </persName>
                        <occupation>Showman</occupation>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div type="chapter" n="1">
                <head> I. The Elephant Man </head>
                <div type="paragraph" n="1">
                    <p>IN the Mile End Road, opposite to the <placeName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q7374421">London Hospital</placeName>, 
                        there was (and possibly still is) a line of small shops. Among them was a vacant greengrocer’s which was to let. 
                        The whole of the front of the shop, with the exception of the door, was hidden by a hanging sheet of canvas on which was 
                        the announcement that <persName ref="#Merrick">the Elephant Man</persName> was to be seen within and 
                        that the price of admission was twopence. Painted on the canvas in primitive colours was a 
                        life-size portrait of <persName ref="#Merrick">the Elephant Man</persName>. This very crude production 
                        depicted a frightful creature that could only have been possible in a nightmare. It was the figure of a man with the characteristics 
                        of an elephant. The transfiguration was not far advanced. There was still more of the man than of the beast. This fact—that it was 
                        still human—was the most repellent attribute of the creature. There was nothing about it of the pitiableness of the misshapened or 
                        the deformed, nothing of the grotesqueness of the freak, but merely the loathsome insinuation of a man being changed into an animal. 
                        Some palm trees in the background of the picture suggested a jungle and might have led the imaginative to assume that it was in this 
                        wild that the perverted object had roamed.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="paragraph" n="4">
                    <p>
                        The <persName ref="#Showman">Showman</persName>—speaking as if to a dog—called out harshly: <q>Stand up!</q>
                        The thing arose slowly and let the blanket that covered its  head and back fall to the ground. There stood revealed the most disgusting 
                        specimen of humanity that I have ever seen. In the course of my profession I had come upon lamentable deformities of the face due to injury 
                        or disease, as well as mutilations and contortions of the body depending upon like causes; but at no time had I met with such a degraded or 
                        perverted version of a human being as this lone figure displayed. He was naked to the waist, his feet were bare, he wore a pair of threadbare 
                        trousers that had4 once belonged to some fat gentleman’s dress suit.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="paragraph" n="56">
                    <p>
                        He often said to me that he wished he could lie down to sleep <q who="#Merrick">like other people.</q> I think on this last night he must, with some determination, 
                        have made the experiment. The pillow was soft, and the head, when placed on it, must have fallen backwards and caused a dislocation of the neck. 
                        Thus it came about that his death was due to the desire that had dominated his life—the pathetic but hopeless desire to be <q>like other people.</q>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
    
